The Life of Muhammadﷺ,
The Madinan period, volume 1, by Imam Anwar Al-Awlaki
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
الْحَمْدُ لِلَّهِ رَبِّ الْعَالَمِينَ۝
الرَّحْمَٰنِ الرَّحِيمِ۝
مَالِكِ يَوْمِ الدِّينِ۝
إِيَّاكَ نَعْبُدُ وَإِيَّاكَ نَسْتَعِين۝
اهْدِنَا الصِّرَاطَ الْمُسْتَقِيمَ۝
صِرَاطَ الَّذِينَ أَنْعَمْتَ عَلَيْهِمْ غَيْرِ الْمَغْضُوبِ عَلَيْهِمْ وَلَا الضَّالِّينَ۝
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝ بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراَ
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
In sha Allah Ta'ala(اِنْ شَاءالله تعالى), we'll start with the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
I've already covered in the past the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ in Makkah
So, In sha Allah Ta'ala(اِنْ شَاءالله تعالى) in these sessions, we'll talk about the early stage of Madina
and we'll start with Al-Hijrah(الهجرة).
But before that just the word on Seerah(سيرة).
The books of Seerah(سيرة) are concerned with what usually historians are concerned with,
and that's the history of politics and the history of the military engagements.
When it comes to the Akhlaaq(أخلاق) of Rasool Allahﷺ, you'd find those in the books of Hadith(حديث).
If you're interested in the Shamael(شمائل) of Rasool Ullah,
which are issues relating to his character, you would find those in books of Shamael(شمائل).
However, the books of Seerah(سيرة) usually cover the political and military aspects of the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And that's why many of our scholars called Seerah(سيرة), Maghazi(مغازي),
Maghazi(مغازي) means, battles.
However, will try to bring in, the verses of Qur'an
that relate to the events that were happening in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ
because Qur'an would comment on events that happened in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
sometimes the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an would proceed an event,
sometimes Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an would come concurrent with an event
and sometimes the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an would come to comment on an event.
So, for example, you have Ghazwa-Tul-Anfaal(غزوة الأنفال) was revealed, talking about the Battle of Badr(بدر),
and what happened therein.
The Battle of Uhud(أحَد), you have the end of the Surah(سورة) of Al-Imran(العمران), relates the story of Uhud(أحَد),
Surah-Tul-Hashr(سورة الحشر) talks about the Battle of Bannu Nadhir(بنو نضير).
You have the Surah(سورة) of Al-Munafiqoon(المنافقون) and Surah-Tun-Noor(سورة النور), the Battle of Bann Mustalaq(بنو مصطلق).
And you have Surah-Tul-Ahzaab(سورة الاحزاب) relating what happened in the Battle of the trench.
So, we'll try to bring in these verses that relate to these events in Seerah(سيرة).
We'll start with the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed Ayaat(آيات) in Makkah, talking about Al-Hijrah(ألهجرة).
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
قُلْ يَا عِبَادِ الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا اتَّقُوا رَبَّكُمْ ۚ
لِلَّذِينَ أَحْسَنُوا فِي هَٰذِهِ الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةٌ ۗ
وَأَرْضُ اللَّهِ وَاسِعَةٌ ۗ
إِنَّمَا يُوَفَّى الصَّابِرُونَ أَجْرَهُمْ بِغَيْرِ حِسَابٍ۝
Say O my servants who have believed,
Fear your Lord, for those who do good in this world, is good.
And the earth of Allah is spacious,
indeed the patient will be given their reward without account.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ in this Ayah(آية) says;
وَأَرْضُ اللَّهِ وَاسِعَةٌ ۗ
The earth of Allah is spacious meaning that if you are suffering oppression in Makkah,
then you can move somewhere else,
where you will be able to apply and live the religion of Allahعَزّوجَل.
Mujahid(مجاهد), who's one of Al-Mufassiroon(ألمفسرون), one of the Imams of Tafseer(تفسير).
He says; Commenting about this Ayah(آية)
فَهَاجَرُوْ فِيْهَا وَ جَاهِدُوْ وَعْتَزِلُ الْاَوْسَانْ
He said: Make Hijrah(هجرة) in the land
and fighting the path of Allahعَزّوجَلّ and stay away from the idol worshipping
And Attaa(عطاء), one of the early scholars of this Ummah(امة), he says;
اِذَ دُعِيْتُمْ اِلَى مَعْصِيَّتٍ فَحْرُبُوْ
If you are invited to do a sin, then run away.
So, we should run away from sins.
And these two quotes are in the Tafseer(تفسير) of Ibn Kathir(إبن كثير).
Allahعَزّوجَلّ also says;
وَالَّذِينَ هَاجَرُوا فِي اللَّهِ مِنْ بَعْدِ مَا ظُلِمُوا لَنُبَوِّئَنَّهُمْ فِي الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً ۖ
وَلَأَجْرُ الْآخِرَةِ أَكْبَرُ ۚ
لَوْ كَانُوا يَعْلَمُونَ۝
الَّذِينَ صَبَرُوا وَعَلَىٰ رَبِّهِمْ يَتَوَكَّلُونَ۝
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says; And those, who immigrated for Allah after they have been wronged,
we will surely settle them in this world in a good place,
but the reward of the Hereafter is greater if only they could know.
So notice here,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is promising the ones, who make Hijrah(هجرة) for His sake,
the ones who have been oppressed,
Allah promises them that He will settle them in this world in a good place.
So, what does this mean?
What does it mean, when Allahعَزّوجَلّ says we will settle them in this world in a good place?
Some of the scholars of Tafseer(تفسير) said;
if you look at Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون)
the ones who moved of Makkah and went to Madina.
Later on, every one of them became an Ameer(امير) of a state or a leader of an army.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ gave them a better status in this world than what they had in Makkah, that is in this world.
And in Aakhira(آخرة) Allahعَزّوجَلّ says; But the reward of the Hereafter is greater.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) when he became Khalifah(خليفه)
and he would give money or gifts to the Muhajiroon(مهاجرون),
he would tell them, this is a gift from Allah for you in this world.
But what Allah has reserved for you in the Hereafter is even greater.
And the scholars say, whoever leaves something for the sake of Allah,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ will give him, something better.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
ثُمَّ إِنَّ رَبَّكَ لِلَّذِينَ هَاجَرُوا مِنْ بَعْدِ مَا فُتِنُوا ثُمَّ جَاهَدُوا وَصَبَرُوا
ثُمَّ جَاهَدُوا وَصَبَرُوا إِنَّ رَبَّكَ مِنْ بَعْدِهَا لَغَفُورٌ رَحِيمٌ۝
Then indeed, Your Lord to those who immigrated, after they had been compelled
and thereafter fought and were patient.
Indeed, your Lord after that, is Forgiving and Merciful.
So, Hijrah(هجرة) has a very high status in Islam.
These Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) have you ever asked yourself a question, Where did they stay?
When they moved from Makkah to Madina?
Did they check into hotels?
Or did they stay in refugee camps?
No, they stayed in the houses of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
And that's why we call them Ansaar(أنصار),
that's why we call them, the ones who gave victory to Islam.
Ansaar(أنْصَار) means they gave support, they gave victory to the religion of Allah.
Their houses were opened for Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون),
even though they were very modest houses,
for example Hassan Al-Basri(ألحسن ألبصري) says
that I entered into the rooms of Rasool Allah ﷺ and I could touch the ceiling with my own hand.
And when Rasool Allah ﷺ would pray in the room of Ayesha(عائشه).
You know, every wife of Rasool Allah ﷺ had a room, that was it, just one room.
You know, they didn't have like a kitchen and the living room and balcony and bedrooms, basement.
No, every wife of Rasool Allah, just had one room.
Now, when Rasool Allah ﷺ would pray in the room of Ayesha(عائشه).
He would have to touch her
so that she would move her feet away, so that he can make Sujood(سجود) it was that small.
So for example, in the house of Khabeeb Ibn Isaaf(خبيب إبن إساف),
Talha Bin Obaidillah(طلحه بن عبيدالله) his mother and Sohaib(صهيب), that's where, they stayed.
Hamzah(حمزه) stayed in the house of Sa'ad Ibn Zurarah(اسعد بن زرارة).
Sa'ad Bin Khaisamah(سعد بن خيسمه) all of the bachelors will stay in his house,
so they called it, the house of bachelors.
Ubaidah Bin Harissa(عبيدالله بن حارثه) and his mother
At-Tufail Bin Haris(ألطفيل بن حارث), Tulail Bin Amr(طليل بن عمرو), Al-Hussain Bin Hariss(الحسين بن حارث),
all of them stayed in the house of Abdullah Bin Salamah(عبدالله بن سلمه).
So one thing we can learn is that being generous and being supportive of Muslims
is one of the signs of Eeman(ايمان) and it was one of the signs of Al-Ansaarرضي الله عنهم.
One comparison between the Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina and the Hijrah(هجرة) of Habasha(حبشه)
because, you know, there are two Hijrah(هجرة),
there was the first Hijrah(هجرة) to Al-Habasha(ألحبشه) and then there was the second Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina.
So, what's the difference between the two?
Well, when it comes to the Hijrah(هجرة) to Al-Habasha(ألحبشه), it was more of,
they went there to flee persecution, but they didn't become part of the society in Abyssinia,
they weren't really part of the society, they were secluded.
Therefore their ability to change the society was hindered.
They were like refugees in Abyssinia.
And that's why when they left Abyssinia, they didn't leave a strong Islamic impression behind.
However, the Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina was an Hijrah(هجرة) to establish the Islamic community.
So, there is a big difference between the two.
Some of the virtues of Madina,
Rasool Allah ﷺ asked Allah to make them love Madina.
So, he said;
اَللَّهُمَّ حَبِّبْ إلينا الْمَدِيْنَهْ كَحُبِّنَا مَكَّة اَوْاَشَدّْ
O Allah make us love Madina like we love Makkah or more.
Rasool Allah ﷺ made Dua(دُعَا) that Allahعَزّوجَلّ gives Al-Madina Baraka(بركة),
اَللَّهُمَّ الجْعَلْ بِالْمَدِيْنَهْ ضِعْفَيْ مَا جَعَلْتَ بِمَكَّةْ مِنَّ البَّرَكَة
And this Hadith(حديث) is in Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ),
O Allah, double the Baraka(بركة) double the blessings of Madina, compared to what you have given Makkah
because, who was the one who made Dua(دُعَا), to Allahعَزّوجَلّ to bless Makkah,
it was Ibrahimعليه السّلام.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is asking Allahعَزّوجَلّ, to double that blessing, when it comes to Madina.
Madina is protected from Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال),
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that there are angels on every entrance to Madina protecting it, from Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال).
There is a special reward for being patient on the hardship of Madina
because Madina is, it was difficult to live in Madina at that time.
It was very hot and the environment was harsh.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
وَلَا يُثْبُتُ اَحَدْ عَلى لَأوَآءِهَا اِلَّا كُنْتُ شَفِيْعًا يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in Sahih Muslim(صحيح مسلم),
anyone who's patient on the hardships of Madina, I will be his intercessor on the Day of Judgment,
I will intercede on his behalf on the Day of Judgment.
There's a special blessing of dying in Madina.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
مَنِ السْتَطَاعْ اَنْ يَمُوتَ بِالْمَدِيْنَةِ فَلْيَمُتْ بِهَا فَاِنِّيْ اَشْفَعُ لِمَنْ يَمُوْتُ فِيْهَا
Whoever is able to die in Madina, then let it be so because I will intercede for you on the Day of Judgment.
And this Hadith(حديث) is in Masnad Al-Imam Ahmad(مسند ألإمام أحمد).
You know, Umar Ibn Al-Khattabرضي الله عنه, when he became Khalifah(خليفه).
He wanted to die in Madina and he also wanted to die as a Shaheed(شهيد), he wanted to them both.
So, he would make a Dua(دُعَا) to Allah, saying; O Allah, I want to die as a martyr in the town of your Prophet.
So, his daughter Hafsah(حفصه) would tell him,
O my father, How can you become a Shaheed(شهيد) in Madina, when it's safe?
Madina is the capital of the Muslim Empire.
If you want to die as a Shaheed(شهيد), you need to go to Iraq, you need to go to Syria, not in Madina.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) would say; "If Allah wants something to happen, He will make it happen."
So not, only did Umar(عُمَر) die as Shaheed(شهيد) in Madina,
he died as a Shaheed(شهيد) in the Mosque of Rasool Allah ﷺ and in Salah(صلاة).
Madina is also the refuge of Eeman(إيمان), Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
إن الإيمان ليأرز إلى المدينة كما تأرز الحية إلى جحرها
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in Bukhari(بخاريْ) that
Eeman(إيمان) seeks refuge in Madina or goes back to Madina like a snake would go back to its hole.
Madina cleanses itself from the impure or the unclean.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
وَالَّذِيْ نَفْسِيْ بِيَدِهِ لَا يَخْرِجُ مِنْهَا اَحَدٌ
رَغْبَةً عَنْهَا اِلَّا اَخْلَفَ اللهُ فِيْهَا خَيْرا مِّنْهُ،
اَلَا اِنَّ الْمَدِيْنَةَ كَالْكِيْر، يخْرِجُ الْخَبِيْثَ ، لَا تَقُوْمُ السَّاعَةُ حَتَّي تَنْفِيَ الْمَدِيْنَةُ شِرَارَهَا،
كَمَا يَنْفِيْ الْكِيْرُ خَبَثَ الْحَدِيْدِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; in Muslim(مسلم) in the name of whom, My soul is in his hands,
Nobody leaves Madina because he doesn't want it anymore,
except that Allah will replace him with someone better than him.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ says,
that Madina cleanses itself from the people, who are impure or the people who are evil.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says the day of judgment will not occur until Madina drives out all of the evil people in it,
like the fire would drive out the impurities of iron.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ protects Madina,
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
لا يَكِيدُ أهْلَ المَدِينَةِ أحَدٌ، إلَّا انْمَاعَ كما يَنْمَاعُ المِلْحُ في المَاءِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; Whoever plots against the people of Madina,
Allah will make him dissolve like salt dissolves in water.
This Hadith(حديث) is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
And Madina also is sacred.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ says, you're not allowed to cut down trees in Madina,
you're not allowed to hunt in Madina,
you're not allowed to carry weapons in Madina, because of its sanctity.
So, these are some of the blessings of the Madina of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Before Rasool Allah ﷺ decided to make Hijrah(هجرة), the people of Makkah plotted against him,
they came together, and they started discussing how to deal with the Islamic problem.
Some of them suggested that we should throw Muhammadﷺ in jail,
the response was no, don't do that this is not a good idea.
Because if you throw him in jail, his followers will come and take him out,
they're going to revolt against us.
So, the second suggestion came in and that's to exile, drive them out of Madina.
So, they said no, that's not a good idea, because his talk is very sweet.
So, he's going to deceive other people to believe in him,
and then they're going to come back to you again.
So, the third suggestion was that of obviously who else other than Abu Jahal(أبو جهل),
he said, we should kill him.
And the way to do that is to appoint a strong man from every clan, give him a sharp sword,
and then have them all strike Muhammad(محمد) at once,
so that his blood will disperse among the different clans of Makkah,
so that the family of Rasool Allah ﷺ will not be able to seek revenge.
And then they will ask for blood money and we will be happy to pay it, to them.
They said: This is the suggestion that we adopt.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَإِذْ يَمْكُرُ بِكَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا لِيُثْبِتُوكَ أَوْ يَقْتُلُوكَ أَوْ يُخْرِجُوكَ ۚ
وَيَمْكُرُونَ وَيَمْكُرُ اللَّهُ ۖ وَاللَّهُ خَيْرُ الْمَاكِرِينَ۝
And remember O Muhammad(محمد),
when those who disbelieved plotted against you, to restrain you, which is, to throw you in jail,
or to kill you, or to evict you from Makkah,
but they plan and Allah plans and Allah is the best of planners.
So, they planned to execute Muhammadﷺ.
They wanted to assassinate him, but Allahعَزّوجَلّ will protect him.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ told Muhammadﷺ to recite the following Dua(دُعَا) and this is an Ayah(آية) in Surat Al-Israa(إسرآء).
وَقُلْ رَبِّ أَدْخِلْنِي مُدْخَلَ صِدْقٍ وَأَخْرِجْنِي مُخْرَجَ صِدْقٍ وَاجْعَلْ لِي مِنْ لَدُنْكَ سُلْطَانًا نَصِيرًا۝
And say my Lord cause me to enter a sound entrance,
and to exit a sound exit, and grant me from yourself a supporting authority.
So, to cause me to enter a sound entrance is to go to Madina,
and to exit the sound exit is to leave Makkah
and grant me from yourself a supporting authority,
because Allahعَزّوجَلّ is teaching Muhammad(محمد) that this religion is supported by authority.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that Allahعَزّوجَلّ, sometimes could support this religion through authority in ways that
Qur'an(قرآن) cannot support the religion
and that's why Khilafah(خِلَافَه) was a very important concept to the Muslims.
In fact, the Sahabah(صحابه) met to decide the issue of Khalifah(خليفه) before they buried Rasool Allah ﷺ,
as we mentioned in the story of Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه.
Rasool Allah ﷺ set out to prepare for Hijrah(هجرة),
Ayeshaرضي الله عنها said, that one day at mid noon, in the house of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
we saw a man approaching us and he was masked, he covered his face.
So, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابو بكر الصديق) saw that it was Muhammadﷺ.
He said: Muhammadﷺ wouldn't come at this time, except if it's something important.
Because it was at noon people usually sleep at noon.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ came in.
And he said: O Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), have everyone in your house, leave.
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه said;
the only ones, who are in my house are your family, O Rasool Ullah!
Meaning my family is like yours.
You can trust speaking in the presence of my family because they are like your own family.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I was given permission to leave and to make Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina.
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه said;
O Messenger of Allah Can I be your companion?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: yes.
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه started to weep.
Ayeshaرضي الله عنها said;
I never saw somebody weeping because of pleasure, because of joy, like my father that day.
Now, I just want to stop right here and say,
this was not an entertaining journey.
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) knew very well, that is risking his life by being the companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ on Hijrah(هجرة).
So, how come he is crying of joy?
When he knows that he's putting his life on the line.
Brothers and sisters, this shows you the level of sacrifice that Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه is willing to go to,
and it shows you that he's so happy to sacrifice for Rasool Allah ﷺ.
I mean, his heart is not trembling, he's not afraid.
He's crying because of joy, when he knows that he could be killed.
But this shows you, the love that he had, for Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Ullah appointed Ali Ibn Abi Talib(عليابن ابي طالب) to sleep on his bed
and this is another sacrifice because Ali Ibn AbiTalib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was also risking his life.
But these were the Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, this is how far they were willing to go.
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), they left Makkah
and Rasool Allah loved Makkah so much.
So, he looked back and he said;
وَلله اِنَّكِيْ لَخَيْرُ اَرْضِ الله وَاَحَبُّ اَرْضِاللهِ اِلَى الله،
وَلَوْ لَا اَنِّيْ اُخْرِجْتُ مِنْكِيْ مَا خَرَجْت
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: In the name of Allah, you are the most beloved land to Allah.
And if it wasn't that I was driven out from you, I wouldn't have left.
I wouldn't leave Makkah, if I had the choice, but he was driven out of it.
The journey started and Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه for some time would walk ahead of Rasool Ullah,
and then for some time, he would walk behind Rasool Ullah.
So, the Messenger of Allah noticed that and then he asked Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
how come sometimes you walk in front of me and sometimes you walk behind me?
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه said;
When I remembered that somebody could ambush you from in front of us,
I walk ahead of you
and then I remember that somebody could be pursuing us, so I walked behind you.
Then Rasool Allah ﷺ said: O Abu Bakr(ابو بكر)
would you rather have harm happened to you or to me.?
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه said: O Messenger of Allah, I would rather have it, happened to me and not to you.
And then they reach to the cave, so Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه went into check the cave
to make sure that there's no snakes, there's no scorpions, there's no ambush.
And then he told Rasool Allah ﷺ to come in.
When they were in the cave, the Kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
succeeded in following their tracks
until they reached to the mouth of the cave.
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه told Rasool Allah ﷺ,
يا رسول الله
O Messenger of Allah,
if one of them would stare right under their feet, they would see us,
they were right there at the mouth of the cave.
Rasool Allah ﷺ with all confidence. He said;
يَا اَبَا بَكْر
O Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), What do you think about two men, if Allah is their third.
مَا ظَنُّكَ بِاثْنَيْنْ الله ثَالِثُهُمَا
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), how would you regard the safety of two people,
who had Allah, as their third companion.
You know what stop them from entering the cave.?
It was a web of a spider.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says about the web of the spider.
وَإنَّ أَوْهَنَ الْبُيُوتِ لَبَيْتُ الْعَنكَبُوتِ
The most feeble of houses, is the house of a spider
with one finger you could tear down the whole web.
So, this feeble weak web
was the soldier of Allah, that stopped the disbelievers from entering into the cave.
And this shows us that Allahعَزّوجَلّ can choose sometimes the weakest of His creation, to be His soldier.
This story of the web of the spider is an agreeable narration, it is Hassan(حسن).
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
If you do not aid him, Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed this Ayah(آية) later on.
This Ayah(آية) is in Surat-Taubah(سورةالتوبة), it's few years after the Hijrah(هجرة).
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ is speaking to the Sahabah(صحابه) and telling them
if you do not aid him, Allah has already aided him.
You know, that day when Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) was the only companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and the Kuffar(كفار) were surrounding the cave,
none of you were around and Allah didn't need you to support His Prophet.
So, Allah is telling the Sahabah(صحابه), if you do not aid him now, Allah has already aided him.
إِلَّا تَنْصُرُوهُ فَقَدْ نَصَرَهُ اللَّهُ
إِذْ أَخْرَجَهُ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا ثَانِيَ اثْنَيْنِ إِذْ هُمَا فِي الْغَارِ إِذْ يَقُولُ لِصَاحِبِهِ
إِذْ يَقُولُ لِصَاحِبِهِ لَا تَحْزَنْ إِنَّ اللَّهَ مَعَنَا
فَأَنْزَلَ اللَّهُ سَكِينَتَهُ عَلَيْهِ وَأَيَّدَهُ بِجُنُودٍ لَمْ تَرَوْهَا
وَجَعَلَ كَلِمَةَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا السُّفْلَىٰ ۗ وَكَلِمَةُ اللَّهِ هِيَ الْعُلْيَا ۗ
وَاللَّهُ عَزِيزٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
When those, who believed had driven him out as one of two
when they were in the cave, and he said to his companion.
So notice here, Allah is calling Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) as the companion of Rasool Allah,
that's an honor to Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه,
لِصَاحِبِهِ
his companion.
Do not grieve indeed Allah is with us and Allah sent down his tranquility upon him,
and supported him with soldiers, you did not see.
One of these soldiers is a spider,
and made the word of those who disbelieved the lowest while the word of Allah that is the highest
and Allah is exalted in Might and Wise.
So, the soldiers of Allah referred to in this Ayaah(آية) are the angels.
These are the unseen soldiers.
But then you also have the spider, which was a seen soldier.
Now, they stayed in the cave for three days,
during those three days, Abdullah(عبدالله) the son of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) would spend a day in Makkah,
listening to conversations ears dropping,
to see what they're saying about Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
and then he would go at night and spend it with Rasool Allah and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) in the cave.
And he would have Aamir Bin Fuhairah(عامربن فحيرة), the servant of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) follow him with his sheep.
So, this has a double purpose
the sheep will provide milk to the prophet and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر).
And the sheep will also cover the tracks of Abdullah(عبدالله) and Aamir(عامر),
so that no one will know, where they went,
and this carried on for three days.
And then the guide showed up, which was Abdullah Bin Uraiqat(عبد الله بن اريقط),
he was a Mushrik(مشرك) a disbeliever, but because he had an alliance with people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
Rasool Allah ﷺ hired him to be their guide.
So, he was the one, who will take them through a different route than the usual one that people usually take.
When they travel from Makkah to Madina.
They set on, the trip to Madina,
they did not follow the regular route, but they went on the coast, coastline.
They followed the coastline, until they reached to Madina.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) set a bounty on Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
100 camels each dead or alive.
And they were sending out their messengers to convey the news to the Bedouins of the desert.
The experts of the routes of the desert
telling them that, bring us Muhammadﷺ, Dead or Alive or Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) we'll give you 100 camels each.
Suraqah Bin Malik(سُراقه بن مالك) was the head of one of these Bedouin tribes.
He said, I was sitting in a gathering of my people,
when a man showed up and said, I saw two men in the horizon.
And I think that these are the two men Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are looking for!
Suraqah(سُراقه) said, I told him, No, these two men were just here a while ago and they just left.
He said, I told them that to deceive him,
but I knew or I felt that those men were Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
but I just told him that because I wanted to get the camels for myself.
So, Suraqah(سُراقه) said, I stayed in the gathering for a while so that they wouldn't be suspicious.
And then I left, I went to my house and I told my servant to go and prepare my horse, the saddle and all
and to hide it behind a mountain or a hill.
And I left from the back door, and I was carrying my spear and he said my spear was dragging on the ground.
Why? Because spear is long, so he didn't want anybody to see it, so he was dragging it.
And then he said I mounted my horse and I went to the direction that, that man saw the two men.
And it was as I thought the two men were Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر).
So, now you only have a few meters between Suraqah(سراقه) becoming a millionaire,
one hundred camels each, he's right there.
Suraqah(سراقه) says; Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) was looking back,
while Muhammadﷺ was reciting Qur'an and he never looked back.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was confident that Allahعَزّوجَلّ will give him victory, while Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) was very concerned,
not for himself but concerned for the safety of Muhammadﷺ.
So, he was staring back, while Muhammadﷺ was reciting Qur'an.
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) told Rasool Allah ﷺ that somebody pursuing us,
Rasool Allah ﷺ made a Dua(دُعَا) and the horse of Suraqah(سُراقه) sank in the sand,
and Suraqah(سُراقه) fell off his back.
Suraqah(سُراقه) said: So, I cast lots, you know, they had all of these superstitious beliefs.
He cast lots, Should I follow them or shouldn't I follow them?
The Lots told me that I shouldn't follow them.
But I insisted on following them, his greed, drived him further.
So, what's the point of casting the lots, if you're going to disobey them anyway,
he followed them, another time and the same thing happened.
He fell off his horse and he said, This never happened to me, I never fell off my horse
The third time it happened to him.
He said a cloud of dust exploded in my face from in front of my horse.
So, I knew that Allah supporting this man,
so I rushed towards him asking him to grant me peace.
Suraqah(سُراقه), who was pursuing Muhammadﷺ now became the pursuit.
Suraqah(سُراقه) who thought that he could kill Muhammadﷺ is now worried for his own safety
and he's asking Muhammadﷺ to grant him peace.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him; I grant you peace.
Suraqah(سُراقه) told him, write that down for me on a piece of paper.
I want to make sure write it down for me.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told Aamir Bin Fuhairah(عامربن فحيرة)
to write down a document stating that Rasool Allah ﷺ is granting Suraqah Bin Malik(سُراقه بن مالك) peace.
Suraqah(سُراقه) sticks this piece of cloth or whatever in his pocket, and years passed by.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) eight or nine years later, he was arrested.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was laying siege to At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف)
and when they were going to kill him.
He pulled that document out and he told them this is a paper a document from Rasool Allah ﷺ granting me peace,
that document saved his life.
Now Suraqah(سُراقه) went back
and he told the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) that you're not gonna find Muhammadﷺ, forget about it.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, to weaken anybody who's trying to pursue us,
drive them away from us.
So, Suraqah(سراقه) who was trying to arrest them now, is their guard,
Suraqah(سراقه) became a bodyguard for Muhammadﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), visited a tent
In front of this tent was a woman, an old woman, her name is Ummo Ma'abad(أم معبد).
This was a very generous woman, anybody who would pass by, she would feed them.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) got there, she didn't provide them with anything.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ asked her if she has anything to spare.
She said: If I had anything you wouldn't have to ask.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ saw in the corner of her tent a very weak goat.
So, he asked her: what's the problem with that goat?
She said, that goat is too weak to go out with the rest of the flock, to feed.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Is there any milk in her?
She said she's weaker than that.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Will you allow me to milk her,
She said: Go ahead.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ goes to milk that goat and he asks for a big container, not a cup, a big container.
And then he touches the goat and he starts milking it.
And milk is flowing out, until it fills the container, and all of this foam on top of the milk.
And then he gives it to Ummo Ma'abad(أم معبد) first.
So, she drinks
and then he gives it to Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) and Aamir(عامر) and Abdullah Bin Uraiqat(عبدالله بن اريقط), they all drink
and he's the last to drink and he said the servant of the people is the last to drink.
So, he was the last to drink.
And then he left and there was still a lot of milk in that container.
So, the husband of Umm Ma'abad(أم معبد) comes back with the flock, with his flock of sheep.
And he sees this milk and he says Ummo Ma'abad(أم معبد), where does, this milk come from?
She said: A blessed man, visited us.
And he's the one, who milked the she goat.
He asked her to describe this man to her.
Umm Ma'abad(أم معبد) gave a description of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
that remains, until this day as one of the best descriptions ever given about Rasool Allah ﷺ,
even though she only met him once.
And I will read to you her description of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
She said: I saw him to be a man of evident splendor,
fine in figure,
his face handsome, slim in form,
his head not too small, elegant and good looking,
his eyes large and black,
his eyelids long his voice deep,
very intelligent,
his bros high and arched,
his hair in plates, his neck long and his beard thick.
He gave an impression of dignity when silent
and of high intelligence when he talked.
His words were impressive.
And he was decisive, not trivial, not trite.
His ideas like pearls moving on their string.
He seemed the most splendid and fine looking man from a distance
and the very best of all from close by,
medium and height.
The eye not finding him too tall nor too short.
tree branch as it were, between two others,
but he was the finest looking of the three.
The best proportioned,
he was the center of his companions attention.
When he spoke they listened well.
And if he ordered the hurried to obey,
a man well helped, well served, never solemn, never refuted.
Her husband said;
this man must be Muhammad(محمد), the one whom Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are pursuing.
If I meet him.
I will pledge allegiance to him and become Muslim.
Now by the way, Ummo Ma'abad(أم معبد) did pledge allegiance to Rasool Allah ﷺ and she became Muslim.
Some lessons from Hijrah(هجرة).
Number one, the concept of Hijrah(هجرة).
There are two types of Hijrah(هجرة).
There's figurative Hijrah(هجرة) and there's the literal Hijrah(هجرة).
The figurative Hijrah(هجرة) is as was mentioned in a Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ in An-Nasae(ألنسائ)
أَنْ تَهْجُرَ مَا كَرِهَ رَبُّكَ عَزّ وجَل
Hijrah(هجرة) is to leave what Allahعَزّوجَلّ dislikes.
So, this is a figurative Hijrah(هجرة), it is to emigrate from the state of sin to the state of obeying Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in Qur'an
وَالرُّجْزَ فَاهْجُرْ
Stay away from impurities,
make Hijrah(هجرة) from impurities from idol worshipping from evil.
And this type of Hijrah(هجرة) is mandatory on everyone.
All of us have to leave the state of sin, to the state of obedience.
Then we have the literal Hijrah(هجرة) and that is to move from one land to another,
you loof from the land of evil to the land of good.
Examples of that are the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه),
or the Hijrah(هجرة) of the man from the children of Israel(اسرائيل) who killed 100 people.
And then he went to consult the scholars.
So, the scholar told him, Allah will accept your repentance, but you have to move from this town.
Because it's the town of evil and go to that other town
because you'll find there in people who will support you, in worshipping Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Benefits of Hijrah(هجرة).
Hijrah(هجرة) can cause an economic boom.
Examples of that,
Grenada, for example, Grenada, the Muslim Grenada at the last Islamic state, in Andalusia(أندلسيه),
when the Christian north, the Spaniards started taking over conquering Islamic land
the Muslims would leave, and they would settle in southern Spain in Grenada(غرناطه).
So, there was a population boom, it reached to over 2 million.
But these are men, who came in with their skills with their abilities as merchants,
their abilities as farmers.
So, Grenada flourished and it became the wealthiest state in all of Europe.
What caused that, major part was due to the Hijrah(هجرة) of the Muslims from northern Spain, to the southern Spain.
The same thing is, for example, happened in the US,
happened in for example Holland earlier a few centuries before,
when all of the for example, the Calvinists, the Protestants moved from some parts of Europe to Holland.
So, Hijrah(هجرة) brings the talents of people together, and a small village could turn into a huge city.
Because of Hijrah(هجرة), you have all of the minds coming together.
For example, now you have an immigration of Muslim minds going to the Western world.
So, the Muslim land is deprived from their abilities, while they are flooding towards the west,
and the fruit of their knowledge is given in western countries, while their Muslim lands are deprived of that.
Hijrah(هجرة) represents the manifestation of the conflict between good and evil.
If we go back to the first days of Da'wah(دعوة),
when Rasool Allah ﷺ was for the first time exposed to Revelation.
And he just knew that he has become a Prophet,
he came down from the cave and he was very terrified and worried.
So, he went to his wife, Khadijahرضي الله عنها and he told her to wrap him in a garment.
That's when the verses of
يَا أَيُّهَا الْمُزَّمِّلُ
and
يَا أَيُّهَا الْمُدَّثِّرُ
were revealed.
So, Khadijahرضي الله عنها told Muhammadﷺ, why don't we go to my uncle and consultant him.
Waraqa Bin Nofal(ورقه بن نوفل) was a wise old man, who was literate and he studied the early scriptures.
And he read the books of the Jewish and the Christian faith.
So, he was a knowledgeable man,
relatively speaking in the environment of Arabia.
So, they went to Waraqa Bin Nofal(ورقه بن نوفل) and they talked to him,
and Waraqah(ورقه) asked Muhammadﷺ, he said O Nephew, What do you see?
So, Waraqah(ورقه) is asking Muhammadﷺ and telling him, what do you see?
Rasool Allah ﷺ explained to him, what happened?
Waraqa Bin Nofal(ورقه بن نوفل) said;
This was the angel Jibril(جبريل), who used to come down to Musa(موسى).
How I wish, I were a young man again.
I hope, I am still alive, when your people exile you.
Now this last statement was a shock to Muhammadﷺ.
My people will exile me, how would that happen?
You need to keep in mind that Muhammadﷺ was the most beloved man in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So, what would cause them to drive him out of Makkah?
Plus, in the tribal society, the tribe is everything and the tribe doesn't forsake any if its members,
so how could it happen that Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), noble tribe of Arabia would drive out one of its members.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ asked, Waraqah(ورقه), he said: Are they going to exile me?
Waraqah(ورقه) replied: Yes.
No one has ever received what you have, without being treated as an enemy.
If I am alive when your time comes, I will give you every help.
So, Waraqa Bin Nofal(ورقه بن نوفل) is speaking about a reality of the history of the Da'wah(دعوة).
When a person comes up with the truth of Islam,
this is what happens, people split into two camps.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says about the people of the Thamood(ثمود).
And we had certainly sent to the Thamood(ثمود), their brother Saleh(صالح) saying worship Allah,
and at once, they were two parties conflicting.
So, Saleh(صالح) who was at the similar position to Muhammadﷺ, very respected in his people.
But when he started preaching the truth to them,
when he started preaching Islam, when he started preaching the oneness of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
They split into two conflicting camps.
And that's why Qur'an is called Al-Furqaan(ألفرقان)
Furqaan(ألفرقان), is the criterion.
It separates between good and evil, it splits the society into two,
and the Battle of Badr(بدر) is also called Furqaan(ألفرقان) for the same reason.
13 years later what Waraqa Bin Nofal(ورقه بن نوفل) predicted, did happen.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says and thus have we made for every prophet and enemy from among the criminals,
but sufficient is your Lord as a guide and the helper.
So, every prophet has enemies.
That is the Sunnah(سنة), the way of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, that's the second lesson.
The third lesson
We can notice from the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, the elaborate planning that went into it.
Number one, Rasool Allah ﷺ visits Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) at noon.
At noon time people are in a siesta because of the heat of Arabia, people don't venture out of their houses.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was out at that time, so that nobody would notice him
and in case somebody does notice him, he was masked, he covered this face.
Number two,
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he came in, to the house of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), he asked him to clear his house.
اَخْرِجْ مِنْ عِنْدَكْ يَا اَبَا بَكْر
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to keep it as a secret.
Number three, he had Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) sleep on his bed.
Number four, the camels were already ready and prepared.
Number five, they left under the cover of darkness and from a backdoor.
Number six, they hired the guide.
Number seven, Madina is north of Makkah,
while Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) headed south, to deceive the disbelievers.
Eight, they went into hiding for three days in the cave.
Number nine, Abdullah Ibn Abu Bakr Siddiqueرضي الله عنه would come to them with information,
he would gather information during the day and come and present to them at night.
Number ten,
Aamir Bin Fuhairah(عامربن فحيرة) brings them food
So, you could see that a lot of planning went into the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and that's how we should conduct our Islamic work.
We shouldn't just say that Masha Allah(ماشاءالله), Allah will take care of everything and Allah will give us Baraka(بركة)
just do what you can do.
And I wish that we would do, what we can do.
But sometimes what this means is, you don't have to do a lot,
just do it you can do it, it doesn't mean that you have to do a lot.
While Rasool Allah ﷺ went to extreme lengths to ensure that he does his best in the planning for Hijrah(هجرة).
When Allahسبحانه تعالى has already promised him with protection.
I mean, he is the Messenger of Allah,
Allah will take care of him, Allah will support him, Allah will, honor him.
So, he doesn't have to do all of this.
But he did it, to teach us that as a Muslim, you have to do your best
you have to do your best and this is Ihsaan(إحسان).
The fourth lesson, from the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
the role of women and we'll try to bring up the role of women in fighting
the role of women in Madina the role of women in Hijrah(هجرة),
because our sisters need to see their role models.
How did we hear about the whole story of Hijrah(هجرة)?
Who was the narrator of the story of Hijrah(هجرة)?
Whether it's in Sahih Al-Bukhari(صحيح ألبخاري), or Sahih Al-Muslim(صحيح ألمسلم)
it was Ayeshaرضي الله عنها,
the whole story of Hijrah(هجرة) was preserved by Ayeshaرضي الله عنها
Number two, Asma Bint Abi Bakr(أسماء بنت أبي بكر), the sister of Ayesha(عائشه),
she tore her griddle to put food into it, to send it to Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
she suffered because of Hijrah(هجرة).
Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) and some men from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) came knocking on the door of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), after they left
and Asmaa(أسماء) opened the door, so Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) asked her,
where is your father?
She said, I don't know where my father is.!
So, he slapped her on her face, so hard.
That was a suffering that she took for the sake of Allahعَزّوجَلّ to protect Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر).
She didn't go screaming and yelling and hollering,
O, yeah, yeah, my father left to Hijrah(هجرة), and just because of one slap.
She was patient, and she stayed quiet.
And you can notice here that she lied.
She said, I don't know where my father is.
And it's allowed to lie in such a situation,
because it's for the protection of a Muslim, Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
So, she suffered because of Hijrah(هجرة).
She was patient, she had Tawakkal In Allah(توكل الى الله),
the father of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), her grandfather
he was already a blind man, he came in and he said;
I see that my son has caused you two sufferings one by him leaving,
and number two by him not leaving you behind any money.
So, Asmaa(أسماء), she was very creative, she went and filled the sack with some rocks
and puts it in the hands of her grandfather and said no, look, he left us a lot of money.
The grandfather said well, it's good that he did so.
She did that to keep him calm.
So she was very content, she was very patient and she had Tawakkal(توكل) on Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
In addition to Ayesha(عائشه) and Asmaa(أسماء) being a women we can also say that,
they are members of the family of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
so we could also use these same examples,
to show the sacrifice that the entire family of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) went into for the sake of Hijrah(هجرة).
Number five, another lesson from Hijrah(هجرة).
You need to choose your companions well,
who did Rasool Allah ﷺ choose to join him in Hijrah(هجرة).
It was Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه, it was the best choice that Rasool Allah ﷺ could make.
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه first of all, he loved Muhammadﷺ, he loved him.
And this love wasn't lip service, it was real.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابو بكر الصديق) cried when he knew that he will be with Muhammadﷺ on Hijrah(هجرة).
And he was so happy that he's going to join Muhammadﷺ.
This shows you his love, he used his entire family to serve Rasool Allah ﷺ in this journey.
He had the highest sense of security, he was very wise man
he was willing to sacrifice his life for Muhammadﷺ, as we talked about last night,
when he went into the cave and when he was walking in front of Rasool Ullah and then walking behind him.
By the way this incident was narrated to us by Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب).
When Umar(عُمَر) was Khalifah(خليفه),
he heard that some people are gathering and they're discussing who's better Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) or Umar(عُمَر).
So, Umar(عُمَر) rushed towards them.
And he said that one day in the life of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) is better than the entire family of Umar(عُمَر).
And he narrative to them, this story,
he said that day in the life of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), the day of Hijrah(هجرة),
that single day is better not only than Umar(عُمَر) and the entire life of Umar(عُمَر)
but better than the entire family of Umar(عُمَر) for all of their lives.
And that shows you the recognition that the Sahabah had of the high status of Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه.
The next lesson in Hijrah(هجرة).
A lot of what Rasool Allah ﷺ was doing at that stage was secret.
He was doing it in secret to preserve Islam and Muslims.
But then there needs to be a balance between secrecy and Da'wah(دعوة).
Da'wah(دعوة) by nature is a public outward act.
So, how do you balance between giving Da'wah(دعوة) and in the same time protecting your organization,
and protecting Islam and Muslims?
We find that for example, in Hijrah(هجرة), we have examples of both, examples of secrecy.
Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) says;
And as I have been told, no one knew of the departure of the Messenger of Allah
except Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) and his family.
These were the only people who knew about the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, it shows that Rasool Ullah wanted to keep it secret.
And for example, when Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) were traveling and they would meet some people
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) would say that Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) was a known man,
while Rasool Allah ﷺ wasn't known in terms of knowing people outside of Makkah
because Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) was a man who traveled a lot, he did business.
So, he knew a lot of people in all of these villages and towns, because of his traveling
while Rasool Allah ﷺ didn't travel outside of Makkah, in the time of Da'wah(دعوة), except to At-Taef(ألطائف)
rest of the time, he spent it giving Da'wah(دعوة) inside Makkah itself.
He never ventured out of Makkah.
So, people outside of Makkah didn't really know him.
They knew about him, but they never really saw him.
So, Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) said that people would come and meet Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) and talk to him.
Now they would ask Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) after they would greet him and ask him, How's he doing?
They're asking. Who's this man with you?
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) would say; This man is a guide, he is showing me the path.
This man is a guide, and he's showing me the path.
Now what these people would understand is that he's the guide, guiding him in the desert
but what Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) really meant is that this man is guiding me towards Allah,
but he put it in this very, in the statement to protect the identity of Rasool Ullah,
he didn't want to tell them that this is Muhammadﷺ,
because now you have 100 camels, there was a bounty on Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, he wanted to protect his identity and the way he did it, was by making the statement.
So, you can see that Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) is not lying.
But they are understanding something different than what he means.
This is, what is called Toriah(توريه), so you can see this secrecy part.
Now when it comes to Da'wah(دعوة),
the identity would need to be exposed for Da'wah(دعوة), so when Rasool Allah ﷺ met with Buraid Al Aslami(بريد الأسلمي).
He did, tell him that I am Muhammadﷺ and he did give him Da'wah(دعوة) and Buraidah(بريدة) became Muslim.
And he joined Rasool Allah ﷺ in the 16 out of his 19 battles.
And he was ahead of his people.
Rasool Allah ﷺ also met with two thieves,
and he gave them Da'wah(دعوة) and they became Muslim.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said, What's your name?
They said: Our name is the Al-Muhanaan(ألمهانان),
Al-Muhanaan(ألمهانان) means the dishonored ones.
The people used to call them the dishonored ones.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told them, No, you are the honored ones.
Another example of Da'wah(دعوة) Rasool Allah ﷺ met with a shepherd.
So, he asked him; Can you give us some milk, the shepherd said none of my goats has milk at the moment.
Rasool Allah ﷺ chose one of them and said would you allow me to milk it?
The shepherd said; Go ahead and Rasool Allah ﷺ did milk it and a lot of milk started flowing out.
And then he gave the shepherd to drink first and then He and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) drank.
So, the shepherd asked Muhammadﷺ, he said;
for heaven's sake, who are you?
I never saw the like of you
Rasool Allah ﷺ responded, do you think you could keep it secret, if I told you.
So, the man said: Yes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I am Muhammad(محمد), the Messenger of Allah.
The shepherd said: You mean you are the one Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) say, claims to be a Sabian(صباء),
Sabian was a degrading accusation that the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) would level towards the Muslims,
they would call them As-Sabioon(ألصابعون), rather than call them Muslim.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes, they do say that.
The man said: Well, I bear witness that you bring the truth, and that only a prophet could do, as you have
I am your follower now.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him; You cannot be that right now.
Come and join us, when you hear, I have declared myself openly.
Rasool Ullah doesn't mean that you cannot follow me in terms of becoming Muslim.
It means you cannot join me now, but he did accept his Islam.
But you cannot join the Islamic Jama'ah(جماعة) at the moment and follow Rasool Allah ﷺ
because Rasool Ullah is still at that secretive stage.
So, you can see here the balance between giving Da'wah(دعوة) and protecting the identity of Rasool Allah ﷺ in being secret.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did declare his identity to people whom he thought would be respondent to the Da'wah(دعوة).
But he didn't give Da'wah(دعوة) to every single person he met in Hijrah(هجرة).
Because all of those people Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) would meet and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) would tell them this is a guide.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not give them Da'wah(دعوة), he did not invite them to Islam.
So, it shows you that there's a balance between the two.
Finally, the Daiyah(داعيه) needs to be financially independent.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) that
I've been given permission to make Hijrah(هجرة)
and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) told him I will join you and be your companion.
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) told Muhammadﷺ, here are two camels for Hijrah(هجرة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
بِثَّمَنْ
I'm going to take the camel and pay for it.
Notice here Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that he's going to pay for that camel.
So, it's important for the Daiyah(داعيه)to be financially independent.
Because what happens is that, when a scholar is on the government payroll,
there's a conflict of interest when that scholar is giving a fatwa(فتوى) on any issue that relates to the government.
When the government is feeding this scholar,
the scholar will be hesitant to criticize the government.
And there's a clear conflict of interest in any Fatwa(فتوى) that relates to politics or relates to issues that upset the government.
And that's why, for example, we hear issues such as scholars giving Fatwa(فتوى), that it's allowed to have interest banks,
banks that deal with the interest system rather than Islamic banks.
This is for example, a fatwa(فتوى) that was forced upon a scholar or a scholar said it to please the government.
That's just an example.
So, it's important for Dua'aa(دعواء) scholars and preachers who invite to Islam to be financially independent.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) were traveling in the desert, at the peak of the summer season,
it was very hot.
Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) says;
Then he took them down, he's referring to the guide
Then he took them down the valley and so to Quba'a(قباء) to the Banni Amr Bin Auf(بني عمرو بن عوف).
It was now Monday the 12th of Rabi Al-Awwal(ربيع اول) and the heat was extreme.
The sun almost having reached its zenith.
So, it was in the middle of summer, very hot
When Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه made Hijrah(هجرة).
The Ansaar(اَنْصار) would go out of Madina every day in the morning in anticipation of meeting Rasool Allah ﷺ and greeting him.
But when the heat becomes too extreme, they would go indoors.
So, one day they went to early in the morning, waiting for Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he didn't show up, they went back in.
There was a Jew who was climbing on, one of their high buildings,
and he saw Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) approaching.
They were dressed in white,
the reason why they were dressed in brand new white clothes,
is because Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) met with Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(زبير بن عوام),
who was coming back from a business trip from Syria,
he just brought with him some new clothes, so he gave Rasool Allah and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) gifts
and these are the clothes that they put on when they went into Madina.
So, this Jew saw Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) approaching,
so he called with the top of his voice he said: O Arabs here is your man, he arrived.
So, the Ansaar(أنْصَار) rushed towards their weapons and marched out to meet Rasool Allahﷺ.
You might wonder how come they went dressed in their weapons or putting their weapons on?
The reason could be that this was the tradition that when you meet somebody or you greet him
you go out carrying your weapons and this is still a tradition in some tribal societies
that when they would meet an important guest, they would take their rifles with them to greet that guest.
The other reason could be that the Baiyah(بيعة) that Ansaar gave to Rasool Allah ﷺ was a Baiyah(بيعة) of protection,
they were offering him protection.
So, they were carrying their weapons with them, to show him that here we are ready and prepared to serve you and protect you.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) arrived and people started greeting them.
Now they arrived at the outskirts of Madina which is Qubaa(قباء)
And Rasool Allah ﷺ stayed there in Qubaa(قباء) for 14 days.
And that is when he built the Masjid(مسجد) of Qubaa(قباء), the first Masjid(مسجد) in Islam.
This Masjid(مسجد) is special,
if you make Wudhuu(وضؤ) at your home and you go to Masjid(مسجد) e Qubaa(قباء) and pray two Rak'a (ركعة),
it counts as if you have made Umrah(عمرة), that is a special virtue to praying in the Masjid(مسجد) of Qubaa(قباء)
Rasool Allah ﷺ stayed in house called, the house of bachelors
because all of the men in there or bachelor, the houseof Sa'ad Bin Khaisamah(سعدبن خيثمه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ stayed there because all of the guests are coming in and out of the house.
So, he didn't want to stay with the family and burden them with, all of these people are coming to meet them.
So, he stayed in this bachelor's house.
And while he was there, Rasool Allah ﷺ sent messengers to Madina, asking them permission to come in.
So, they sent him a large delegation and they came and met Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
اُدْخُلَا آمِنَيْنِ مُطَاعَيْنْ
Come in and you are safe and you will be obeyed.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is not coming to Madina as a guest
he is coming to lead the people of Madina and they came and told him you will be obeyed.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَمَا أَرْسَلْنَا مِنْ رَسُولٍ إِلَّا لِيُطَاعَ بِإِذْنِ اللَّهِ ۚ
Every prophet that we have sent or every messenger that we have sent, we sent them to be obeyed.
So, the people should follow the Messengers of Allah.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ goes into Madina, it was amazing day,
it was a huge celebration,
people came out to greet him, the men came out armed
the Abyssinians were dancing with their spears
women were standing on rooftops,
children were flooding the streets, everybody wants to catch a glimpse of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) says; "The messenger of Allah did come and his companion.
They were among the towns people, even the old people came out to greet them,
climbing on top of houses and shouting which one is he?
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) says. "We never saw such a sight before."
People coming out everybody wants to catch a glimpse of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
people were happy that Rasool Allah ﷺ has arrived.
Anas Ibn Malikرضي الله عنه said; "I witnessed the day, he entered among us
and I witnessed the day, he died.
And I never saw two days as those.
I never saw two days like that in my life."
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) says in another narration;
I witness two days, One day was the brightest and best day in my life.
And that was the day Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) came into Madina.
The other day was the darkest day and the worst day in my life.
And that was the day in which Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away and I've witnessed both of them.
So dear brothers and sisters, the best day in Madina has ever witnessed,
was the day in which Rasool Allah ﷺ came in.
And the worst day in Madina has ever witnessed was the day Rasool Allah ﷺ left.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was offered to stay in every house in Madina,
all of them were welcoming.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to stay with Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار), because Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار) are his relatives.
You see, Hashim(هاشم) married a woman from Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار),
Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار) are from Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج).
Therefore, Abdul Muttalib(عبدالمطلب) his maternal uncles are from Madina from Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I want to stay with Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار).
And then he asked Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار), he said which house of Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار) is closest to me?
So, Abu Ayuub Al-Ansaari(ابوايوب الانصاري) said: My house.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ stayed at the house of Abu Ayuub(ابوايوب).
Rasool Ullah wanted to stay in the lower level
while Abu Ayuub(ابوايوب) was trying to convince him to stay in the upper level, because it was a two story house.
The reason why, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to stay in the lower level is because, people are visiting him.
So, he wanted to make it easy and stay in the lower level, finally Abu Ayuub(ابوايوب) agreed
Abu Ayuub(ابوايوب) says; We had a container filled with water that fell.
So, we were afraid that water would drip on Rasool Allah ﷺ,
so we use our blanket, and me and my wife only had that blanket.
We used it, to soak up the water, and we had to sleep without that blanket."
This is the generosity that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم were offering to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
his only blanket he used it, to soak up water,
just so that a few drops of water wouldn't drip on Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Another example of the generosity of people in Madina Zaid Bin Thabit رضي الله عنه says;
the first gift made to the Messenger of Allah,
after he took up residence in the home of Abu Ayuub(ابوايوب) was brought to him by myself.
It was a big wooden bowl filled with bread,
crumbled up with milk and butter.
I told him that my mother had sent him the bowl.
He commented, May Allah bless her.
Then he called over his companions and they ate.
Then a wooden bowl came from Sa'ad Ibn Ubadah(سعدابن عبادة), it was bread mixed with meat gravy.
Zaid Bin Thabit(زيد بن ثابت) then says,
not an evening went by, without there being at the door of the Messenger of Allah three or four people
who would come, one after the other carrying food
He remained there in the home of Abu Ayuub(ابوايوب) for seven months.
So, you can just imagine the scene of people coming in everybody carrying a plate, to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
these were poor people but they were giving up their food for Rasool Allah ﷺ.
People loved Rasool Allah ﷺ, young girls went in the streets and they were singing,
they were saying we are girls of Bannu Najjar(بنو نجار).
How wonderful if Muhammad(محمد) were our neighbor.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: "Allah knows that my heart loves you all.
Allah knows that my heart loves you all."
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ loved them and they loved him.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ has chosen the people of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) to be the Ansaar(أنْصَار) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
They loved him very much and he also loved them a lot.
Towards the end of his life, he said, If it wasn't for Hijrah(هجرة), I would consider myself to be a member of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
What was the situation of Madina like?
When Rasool Allah ﷺ moved in there, there were five tribes living in Madina.
Three of them were Jewish, and two of them were Arab.
The three Jewish tribes were Bannu Qainuqah(بنو قينقاع), Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير), Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه).
Bannu Qainuqah(بنو قينقاع) lived in the center of Madina, the market place
and they were in the business of jewelry.
They used to live in the outskirts of Madina in forts, but they were driven out in a war between them and other Jews.
So, they ended up settling in the middle of Madina, in the center of the town.
Bannu Nadhir(بنونضير), and Bannu Quraidha(بنوقريظه) lived in the outskirts of Madina.
And they were living in forts they had about 59 fortresses in which they lived in.
Their fighting force was about 2000.
These were the men of fighting age, about 2000.
The Arab tribes were Al-Aos(الاوس) and Al-Khazraj(الخزرج)
and they're fighting force was about 4000.
And they lived inside Madina, one tribe lived in north and the other tribe lived in the south.
So, Madina wasn't really a city in terms of all houses being connected,
but it was a collection of small villages that formed Madina.
So, you'd have living quarters for the Jews and living quarters for the Arabs
and each Jewish tribe was separate and two Arab tribes are also separate.
The livelihoods of the people in Madina was based on agriculture.
It was fertile, and they had palm groves
The farmer would need money throughout the year, until harvest time would come,
So the Jewish tribes would lend the Arabs money and they would charge them interest, for usury,
and this cause some conflict and some bitter feelings between the Arabs and the Jews of Madina.
This is briefly the situation that existed prior to the advent of Islam.
Now when the slam came in, now we have Muslims, you have pagan worshippers and you have Jews.
So, you had different faiths and different ethnic groups inside Madina.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ had to be very careful in dealing with these complications in Madina,
don't think that it was very easy and everybody just became Muslim and everybody loved Rasool Allah ﷺ
and it was very easy to rule over Madina, it was very difficult.
You had people among the Arabs, who were not happy, that Rasool Allah ﷺ was there,
you also had the Jewish tribes who were not happy that Rasool Allah ﷺ was there,
and then among the Arabs, we had Muslim and non Muslim.
So, it was a complicated situation, to give you an example of this complication.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was riding on his donkey and he went towards a gathering
that included Arabs, Muslim and non Muslim and also Jews.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ went to that gathering and when his donkey arrived,
obviously it caused some dust and Abdullah Bin Ubaey(عبدالله بن اُبَيْ),
who later became the head of the Munafiqeen(منافقين),
he said, keep your dust away from us.
And Rasool Ullah did not respond back to him, Rasool Ullah started preaching Islam to them.
He gave them a talk about Islam
When he finished Abdullah Bin Ubaey(عبدالله بن اُبَيْ) said,
Don't come and bother us in our meetings with your talk, stay home,
and whoever comes to visit you, then tell them your stories.
Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحه), who was a Muslim
He said; No, we want him to come to our meetings and talk to us.
And then people started shouting and war was almost going to break out.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ had to calm them down,
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ went to the house of Sa'ad Ibn Ubadah(سعدبن عبادة) and said;
O Sa'ad(سعد) didn't you see, what Abdullah Bin Ubaey(عبدالله بن اُبَيْ) did?
Sa'ad asked him, what happened and when Rasool Allah ﷺ told him.
Sa'ad(سعد) responded back by saying;
O Rasool Allah, Abdullah Bin Ubaey(عبدالله بن اُبَيْ) was a man,
whom his people were almost going to appoint him, King over them.
When you arrived, so he sees that you have stripped him of his kingdom,
you have stripped him of that post.
So, Sa'ad Ibn Ubadah(سعدبن عبادة) is telling, Rasool Allah ﷺ it's understandable that he is against you,
because he was going to be appointed by Al-Khazraj(الخزرج) to be king over them.
So, this was the situation that Rasool Allah ﷺ was dealing with.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته